Guide to the Archives of Irish American United Irish Counties Association Collection AIA.056
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America United Irish Counties Association Collection
1931-2018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kearns, Martin
Archives of Irish America
AIA.056
7.98 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 2 half manuscript boxes, 6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 custom-size artifact box
1 reel
The United Irish Counties Association organized in 1904 as an attempt to reunite again all Irish under one umbrella organization. The UICA aims to promote and preserve Irish heritage and culture. Its Annual Feis brings together Irish talent for a celebration of music, dance, and song. The collection consists of annual Feis programs, newspaper clippings, papers from Irish Institute, and photographs of United Irish County Societies activities.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
An additional acceretion was donated by Martin Kearns, June 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.103.
In March 2025, Marion Casey donated an accretion of ephemera, photographs, and objects; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2025.036. The cape that was included in this accession was likely donated by Kathleen O'Sullivan in 2011.
Arrangement
Files are organized alphabetically. The Annual event seems to have changed names between "ball" and "dance" over the years; these files are organized chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Irish county organizations were first organized in New York City in the late 1840s. The early societies were for the most part purely social organizations, but in the 1870s some of them started to offer benefits for sickness and death. As the Irish settled into different areas of the city, individual county societies became more prevalent. With the growth of Irish sports, these county societies were even more important. The United Irish Counties Association organized in 1904 as the Irish Counties Athletic Union, as an organization to coordinate and provide venues for sporting events and dances. The goal was to reunite the individual Irish Societies under one umbrella organization, to establish a "central unit of administration to guide and coordinate the activities of the Irish County Organizations," according to the history written by James Comerford, former President of the UICA. (See Box 3, Folder 18.) In 1907, the name was changed to United Irish Counties Association (UICA) with the aim of providing more Irish activities in addition to sports and dances. The purpose of the UICA as articulated in its incorporation papers is to "aid and encourage the members of the Irish race in this State (New York) in taking advantage of all the educational and business opportunities; to furnish information and advice to them on all matters relating to high schools, night schools, trade schools, civil service and commercial opportunities." The organization also promotes activities to preserve and promote the traditional culture if the Irish. This is realized in the Feis, an annual celebration of Irish music, dance, song and athletics.
For more information, visit: http://www.uicany.org/United_Irish_Counties/History.html
Custodial History
In 1998, Martin Kearns donated materials collected by Peter Nesdale, which had been sent to him by Mel Keighran. This gift included records from the 1940s-1950s and commemorative buttons. Rita and Jim Fitzpatrick sent a gift of annual feis programs, newspaper clippings, papers from Irish Institute, and photographs of United Irish County Societies activities. Accession number associated with the Fitzpatrick gift is 2012.030.
A photograph of the 1944 installation of officers was donated by Brian McGinn in 2011.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish American County Society Records (AIA 003) Emerald Society Records (AIA 057) James J. Comerford Papers (AIA 010)
Missing Title
Archives of Irish America County Society Records (AIA 003)
James J. Comerford Papers (AIA 010)
Emerald Society Records (AIA 057)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of souvenir journals from the annual dinners and dances of the Association. Also included are programs and documentation on the Feis, a festival celebrating Irish culture and music. A scrapbook kept by Rosalie Fitzpatrick on the Feis is also included in the collection. The unbound scrapbook contains originals and photocopies of many of the Feis programs as well as newspaper clippings and articles. One of the articles is written by Ms. Fitzpatrick herself in response to an article written by a Ms. Miller on the meaning and tradition of the Feis. Also of interest is a history of the UICA written by James Comerford, one-time President of the Association. A copy of the article is contained in Ms. Fitzpatrick's scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 18).
Souvenir programs.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Folk festivals; Kearns, Martin; United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.
- American Irish Historical Society, 1940, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- American Irish Historical Society, Annual Banquet (41st) [Photograph], Feb 19, 1938 (Box Shared Tamiment AIAXOS001, Folder 1)
- Annual Ball: Committee, 1975-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual Banquet Journal, 2011-2015 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
- Annual Banquet journals, 2015-2018 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 11-12)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal: Diamond Jubilee, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1991, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Annual Ball photograph, 1953 (Box Shared Tamiment 031, Folder 5)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Annual Banquet, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Annual Banquet, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Annual Feis: Circulars, 1984-2008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Annual Feis: Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Annual Feis: Delegates Meeting, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Annual Feis: Documentation, 1942 (Box Shared Tamiment 172, Reel 056.0001)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This item requires use of a microfilm reader for access.
- Annual Feis: Documentation, 1951-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Annual Feis: Flyer, circa 1967 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1963-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Annual Feis: Program, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Annual Feis: Program, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Annual Feis: Syllabus, 1964, 1981-1989, 1997-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Auditors Report, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Certificate of Incorporation, 1936-03-16 (Box Shared Tamiment AIAXOS001, Folder 1)
- Community Action Bureau, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Community Action Bureau publication: The Needs of the American-Irish Community in the City of New York, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Constitution, 1942, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Constitution, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1976-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Cumann Na Gaedilage, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- The Dark Horse, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Delegates Meetings, Newsletter, 1984-2003 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Diamond Jubilee Dinner Dance -- Committee Meeting Announcement, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Ephemera: Commemorative Ribbons, 1941-1954 (Box 4)
- Feis History/Background Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Feis Winners Concert Program, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Fitzpatrick Feis Programs, 1934-1945, 1947-1989, 1996-2001 (Box 7, Folder 5-8, Box 8, Folder 1-3)
- Fitzpatrick Feis Syllabus, 1940-1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Fran John Garvey via Brian Fitzpatrick, 1934-1945, 1957-1966, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 5, Box 9, Folder 1)
- Glee Club, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Golden Jubilee Program, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Grand Festival: Yonkers Raceway, Jun 16, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Installation of Officers, 1944, 1975-2007, undated (Box Shared Tamiment AIAXOS001, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 13, Box 6)
- Irish Ball, 1910 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Irish Ball [Photograph], Nov 4, 1932 (Box Shared Tamiment AIAXOS001, Folder 1)
- Irish Directory, 1983 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 13)
- Irish Festival Souvenir Program, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Irish History, 1951-1955, 1966, 1968, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
- Irish Institute, 1966-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Irish Year Book, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Ladies Auxiliary -- By-laws and Constitution, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Ladies Auxiliary -- Cape, undated (Box 12)
- Ladies Auxiliary -- Minutes, 1940-1952 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Medal -- 3rd Grand Festival (Peter Tuohy), 1992 (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Feis Syllabus Materials, 1973-1979, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Monthly Meeting Notices, 1982-1989, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- New York Irish Feis Day: New York World's Fair, Aug 1, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Office of the National Historian - Ancient order of the Hibernians in America, 1945-1948 (Box 9, Folder 7, Box 10, Folder 1)
- Photographs -- General, 1946-1956, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Photos from Rita and Jim Fitzpatrick, 1933-1937, 1949, 1956, 1959, 1969, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
- Rita Fitzpatrick UICA Feis Scrapbook: Annual Celebrations, 1934-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Rita Fitzpatrick UICA Feis Scrapbook: Articles and Personal Notes, 1979, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Rita Fitzpatrick UICA Feis Scrapbook: Photographs and Newsclippings (photocopies), 1938-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Rita McLoughlin Fitzpatrick UICA Feis singing award medals, 1934-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Sport, 1934, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Summary of Meeting with Consulate General of Ireland, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 14)
- United Irish Counties Association Annual Feis, 1941, 1944-1945, 1948, 1955-1957, 1959, 1963, 1965, 1968-1970, 1973, 1976-1979, 1981-1983, 1989, 1996, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 10, Folder 5-6)
- United Irish Counties for the U.S.O., 1942 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Yearbook, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 15)